<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>More Shots On Goal</title>
  <link href="https://github.com/borkdude/quickblog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://github.com/borkdude/quickblog"/>
  <updated>2025-05-01T05:51:43+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://github.com/borkdude/quickblog</id>
  <author>
    <name>Quick Blogger</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://github.com/borkdude/quickblog/apps-for-ultralight-flying.html</id>
    <link href="https://github.com/borkdude/quickblog/apps-for-ultralight-flying.html"/>
    <title>Which app should I use while flying my ultralight aircraft?</title>
    <updated>2025-03-08T23:59:59+00:00</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is introductory post. I’ll share more over time. Originally posted here: https://ultrapilot.substack.com/p/which-app-should-i-use-while-flying</em></p><h2 id="background">Background</h2><p>For a number of years, I’ve been flying general aviation and light sport aircraft. The last few years have been dedicated to flying powered parachutes (or PPCs - a very simple, safe and low-cost way to fly).</p><p>When I started flying powered parachutes, my aircraft had only engine gauges and an altimeter. Upon recommendation from friends, I began exploring a few different apps which used GPS to track my flight, show my GPS altitude and ground speed. After trying more than two dozen apps, including some of the most popular flying applications, I’ve settled on a core set of features that I use.</p><p>This publication is an effort to share what I have learned along the way and hopefully save others some time.</p><h2 id="the_beginning">The Beginning</h2><p>The question I started with was:</p><h3 id="which_apps_can_track_my_flight%3F">Which apps can track my flight?</h3><p>Here is a list of most of the apps I have tried. In later posts I’ll compare features and show some screenshots. Many of them are for iOS only, but some are available for Android as well. The apps fell into two main categories: Aviation apps and Navigation/Outdoor Exploration apps. Some of the Navigation apps, mostly meant for hikers, included much of the functionality I needed.</p><ul><li>Air Navigation Pro</li><li>Avare</li><li>AvareX</li><li>Avioniq (Garmin watch app)</li><li>CalTopo</li><li>EnRoute</li><li>Foreflight</li><li>FlyQ EFB</li><li>Gaggle Flight Recorder</li><li>Gaia GPS</li><li>Garmin Explore</li><li>Garmin Pilot</li><li>GPS Tracks</li><li>GPX Tracker</li><li>iFly EFB</li><li>Levil Aviation</li><li>MasterPilot</li><li>MotionX GPS (no longer available)</li><li>onX Offroad</li><li>Organic Maps</li><li>OsmAnd Maps</li><li>PPG Flyer (no longer available)</li><li>PPGpS (Android)</li><li>SeeYou Navigator</li><li>Topo Maps+</li><li>WorkOutdoors (Apple Watch)</li><li>Wingman</li><li>xcNav</li></ul><p>The main features I looked for were the following:</p><ol><li>Record my flight<ul><li>a. Show tracks on the map</li></ul></li><li>Display Metrics<ul><li>AGL - altitude above origin (takeoff location/landing zone)</li><li>MSL - altitude above sea level (for communicating location over radio to other aircraft)</li><li>Distance from origin (so I know how far I have to go before I land, and for reporting distance from airport to other aircraft)</li><li>Direction to origin (so I know which direction to fly to get home)</li><li>Flight duration (how long have I been flying?)</li><li>Satellite basemap (when flying low and slow, use of barns, rivers, etc. for reference is very useful)</li><li>Offline maps</li><li>Traffic on map - ADS-B device integration and/or web-based traffic data (I fly near a university with substantial flight training traffic. Seeing other aircraft on the map helps me stay out of their way, and also communicate better)</li><li>Split-screen enabled - Ability to show the app plus another split-screen on my iPad (some apps do not have this enabled)</li><li>Export GPX file</li></ul></li></ol><p>Other good, features I looked for were:</p><ul><li>Additional metrics<ul><li>Total Distance</li><li>Average speed</li><li>Elevation chart</li><li>Auto-detect takeoff and landing</li><li>Auto-detect wind direction</li></ul></li><li>Review my flight (playback)</li><li>Color-coded altitude and groundspeed</li><li>Offline maps</li><li>Aviation basemaps</li><li>Aviation data (airports, METAR/TAF, NOTAMS/TFRs)</li></ul><p>I’ll share my experiences here. Fell free to drop me a line and share what you fly with or any questions you have (like “does the Levil Aviation Astro+ work with Garmin Pilot?”).</p><p>Fly safeI’ll share my experiences here. Fell free to drop me a line and share what you fly with or any questions you have (like “does the Levil Aviation Astro+ work with Garmin Pilot?”).</p><p>Cheers,</p><p>Cam.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
</feed>
